Finding Aid for the Getty Oral History Program Interviews Overseen/Conducted by University of California, Berkeley, 2015-ongoing, J. Paul Getty Trust IA10030
Institutional Records and Archives
Getty Oral History Program interviews, overseen/conducted by University of California, Berkeley,
2015-2022
Institutional Records and Archives
Ruscha, Edward
Meeker, Martin
J. Paul Getty Trust
Agnew, Neville,, 1938-
Druzik, James R.
Irwin, Robert, 1928-
Terrill, Joey, 1955-
Stoner, Joyce Hill
Considine, Brian B.
Kren, Thomas, 1950-
Hamma, Kenneth
Price, Merritt
Schilling, Michael R.
Szafran, Yvonne
Siart, William (Bill)
Kozberg, Joanne Corday
Taylor, Peter J.
Podany, Jerry
Gaehtgens, Thomas W., 1940-
IA10030
252 GB
2.4 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
Records currently consist of printed transcripts and flash drives containing Word, PDF, MP3 and MP4, wav, and raw video files, dating 2015-2022, of the oral histories created as a part of the new 2015- Getty Oral History Program initiated by Trust President James Cuno and overseen/conducted by Martin Meeker, oral historian with The Oral History Center, Bancroft Library, University of California Berkeley.
The Getty Oral History Program, 2015-ongoing
The J. Paul Getty Trust has had a number of internal oral history initiatives throughout its brief history. The projects have fallen into rough categories of Interviews Regarding the Study of Art History (1986, 1988, 1990), Interviews with Art Historians (1991-2002) and Interviews of Significant Getty Trustees and Staff, organized by historical period and institutional role of interviewee (1999-2010). The interviewers of the first two categories were Richard Candida-Smith and, to a lesser extent, Claire Lyons, while the interviewer of the third category was Eric Abrahamson.
The Getty is a young institution of major consequence in its field, perceived by many to be among the leaders - and sometimes being the leader - in specific aspects of its field's work. Though informative, none of the earlier initiatives have fully expressed the Getty's exceptional nature or addressed the transformative quality of its leadership. Additionally, many of the earlier interviews are closed for the life of the participant and therefore currently unavailable for research. The new 2015-ongoing initiative, proposed by President and CEO James Cuno, is intended to fill these gaps, producing publicly accessible interviews that discuss the Getty's extraordinary role in the world. Being a young institution, the Getty has access to all but the very first generation of its predecessors and colleagues, making this a timely project.
In this Getty Oral History Project, oral histories will fall into two broad categories. The existing category "Interviews of Significant Getty Trustees and Staff'' will be continued, commencing with the departure of former President and CEO Barry Munitz in 2006, and using a thematic approach, e.g., "the resolution of the governance crisis in 2006-2007 (Attorney General investigation, Los Angeles (LA) Times articles, etc.)," "the negotiations with Italy and Greece over the return of antiquities," "the hiring of Jim Wood as President/CEO," "the response to the financial crisis," "Jim Wood's tenure as President/CEO," "the development of the individual Programs since 2006," and "reflections of the Trustees upon their departure," etc. In addition, the existing categories "Interviews Regarding the Study of Art History" and "Interviews with Art Historians" will be combined and expanded to include conservators, conservation scientists, relevant arts philanthropists, and art museum directors and curators. The purpose of this category is to capture the current state of the field within which the Getty works and provide a context for understanding the developing role of the Getty within it.
The Getty plans to work with Oral History Center (OHC) of the Bancroft Library at the University of California, Berkeley, to conduct thirty interviews annually, ten from Getty Staff and Trustees and twenty from leaders in its field, beginning with three interviews as a pilot project to assess quality and direction. Within the Getty, internal oversight of the project vests with a team comprised of the Getty's four Program Directors and Trust President, with the VP/COO/CFO, VP/General Counsel, VP Communications, and VP Development providing advice, as necessary.
The J. Paul Getty Trust
The J. Paul Getty Trust is a cultural and philanthropic institution dedicated to the presentation, conservation, and interpretation of the world's artistic legacy. Through the collective and individual work of its constituent programs—the Getty Conservation Institute, the Getty Foundation, the J. Paul Getty Museum, and the Getty Research Institute—the Getty pursues its mission in Los Angeles and throughout the world, serving both the general interested public and a wide range of professional communities in order to promote a vital civil society through an understanding of the visual arts.
The origins of the J. Paul Getty Trust date to 1953, when J. Paul Getty established the J. Paul Getty Museum as a California charitable trust to house his growing art collections. Originally a small, private institution located in Mr. Getty's ranch house near Malibu, the museum moved to the newly constructed Getty Villa in grounds adjacent to the ranch house in 1974. When most of Mr. Getty's personal estate passed to the trust in 1982, the trustees decided that, given the size of the endowment, it should make a contribution to the visual arts and humanities that would reach even beyond the museum. Out of this resolve grew an expanded commitment to the arts in the general areas of scholarship, conservation, and education. Harold M. Williams was the first president and CEO of the Trust, serving from 1981 through 1998. Williams supervised the Trust's development of new programs, with the advice and recommendations of advisors such as Lani Duke and Nancy Englander. The programs included the Center for the History of Arts and Humanities, Art History Information Institute, Conservation Institute, and Center for Education in the Arts, as well as smaller programs, such as the Museum Management Institute and the Program for Art on Film. In 1983 the Trust's name was changed from the J. Paul Getty Museum to the J. Paul Getty Trust to reflect its broader scope, with the museum becoming an operating program of the Trust. As of 2010 the Trust supports and oversees four programs: the J. Paul Getty Museum, the Getty Foundation, the Getty Conservation Institute, and the Getty Research Institute.
Due to expanded operations and limited space at the original J. Paul Getty Museum in Pacific Palisades (near Malibu), the various programs of the J. Paul Getty Trust were located at different sites throughout the Los Angeles basin during the 1980s and mid 1990s. The Trust's vision was to bring together most of their programs at a single site. A roughly 750-acre property in Brentwood (west Los Angeles) was purchased by the Trust in 1983 and the following year the architectural firm Richard Meier & Partners was chosen to design the Getty Center, to house the Trust, its newly created programs, and an additional space for the Museum. Currently, the J. Paul Getty Trust and Getty programs serve a varied audience from both locations: the Getty Center in Los Angeles and the Getty Villa near Malibu, California.
The Oral History Center, Bancroft Library, University of California Berkeley
Since 1954 the Oral History Center of the Bancroft Library, formerly the Regional Oral History Office, has been interviewing leading participants in or well-placed witnesses to major events in the development of Northern California, the West, and the nation. Oral history is a method of collecting historical information through recorded interviews between a narrator with firsthand knowledge of historically significant events and a well-informed interviewer, with the goal of preserving substantive additions to the historical record. The recording is transcribed, lightly edited for continuity and clarity, and reviewed by the interviewee. The corrected manuscript is bound with photographs and illustrative materials and placed in The Bancroft Library at the University of California, Berkeley, and in other research collections for scholarly use. Because it is primary material, oral history is not intended to present the final, verified, or complete narrative of events. It is a spoken account, offered by the interviewee in response to questioning, and as such it is reflective, partisan, deeply involved, and irreplaceable.
Scope and Contents
Records currently consist of printed transcripts and flash drives containing Word, PDF, MP3 and MP4, wav, and raw video files, dating 2015-2022, of the oral histories created as a part of the new 2015- Getty Oral History Program initiated by Trust President James Cuno and conducted by Martin Meeker, oral historian with The Oral History Center (OHC), Bancroft Library, University of California Berkeley. Interviews and video clips may be viewed under the Getty Trust project on the Berkeley Oral History Center website.
All interviews are recorded on high-quality digital video. Each interview is transcribed in its entirety. Draft transcripts are lightly edited by OHC staff and then provided to each interviewee for his/her review and approval. At this point, interviewees are given the opportunity to edit, delete, and/or seal all or portions of their transcript (to the extent permissible under law) for a designated period of time as well. OHC staff then prepare a final transcript, which entails entering the interviewee's edits and preparing a discursive table of contents; if portions of a transcript have been sealed, OHC will prepare two transcripts: an expurgated version for immediate public release and an unexpurgated version that will be placed under seal until the designated release date. Interviewee-approved transcripts are then provided to the Getty to review prior to public release. The Getty has the right to determine if individual transcripts and accompanying audio/visual files (or portions thereof) should be sealed or otherwise put into limited public release (e.g. available only in research libraries) for a designated period time as well. No single transcript or accompanying audiovisual file will be published, deposited in an archive, or otherwise made available to the public until both the interviewee and the Getty provide formal approval. The goal of these measures is to create an environment in which interviewees feel secure in providing as candid and incisive interviews as possible and to protect any proprietary information that may be included in the interviews.
Conditions Governing Access
Unless transcripts have been sealed by the participant, the 2015-ongoing Getty Oral History Program Interviews are unrestricted and open to the public.
The following types of records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Arrangement
Records are organized into two series: I. Interviews with the arts community, 2015-2019; II. Interviews of significant Getty trustees and staff, 2016-2022.
Existence and Location of Copies
In addition to being made available at their home at the Getty, approved interview transcripts along with selected approved video clips drawn from interviews will be posted to the OHC website and cataloged by The Bancroft Library, and listed in the MELVYL and OSKICAT catalogs. The OHC will work with the Getty to publicize the release of the interviews and to encourage the use of the materials by scholars, journalists, activists, and the public at large at a date agreeable to all parties.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records in 2016.IA.34 were deposited with the Institutional Archives in March 2016 (additional clarifications and finalized sets were deposited in March 2017). The records in 2017.IA.61 were deposited with the Institutional Archives in July 2017. The transcripts in 2018.IA.76 were deposited with the Institutional Archives in December 2018 (digital files were not included at that time). Digital files and three transcripts were accessioned in December of 2019 (2019.IA.101) an additonal transcripts were received in August 2021. Additional material was deposited in 2021 (2021.IA.17) and 2023 (2023.IA.14).
Related Materials
J. Paul Getty Trust Oral History Transcripts, 1999-2010. Institutional Archives, Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA10024.
Interviews with Art Historians, 1991-2002. Getty Research Institute, Accession no. 940109.
Art Education History Archives Project, 1998-1999, Getty Education Institute. Institutional Archives, Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA20034.
Historic sites -- Conservation and restoration; Art objects -- Conservation and restoration; Artists -- United States -- 20th century; Getty Conservation Institute; J. Paul Getty Museum
- Interviews with the arts community, 2015-2019; 0.7 Linear Feet; 68.6 GB
  Arrangement
  Interviews are in alphabetical order by the last name of the interviewee.
  Biographical / Historical
  Interviews with the Arts Community includes the continuation of earlier oral history projects "Interviews Regarding the Study of Art History" and "Interviews with Art Historians". The new category, however, has been expanded to include conservators, conservation scientists, relevant arts philanthropists, and art museum directors and curators. The purpose of this category is to capture the current state of the field within which the Getty works and provide a context for understanding the developing role of the Getty within it.
  Scope and Contents
  Records currently consist of the printed transcript and Word, PDF, MP3 and MP4, wav, and raw video files, dating 2015-2019, of the oral histories created as a part of the new 2015- Getty Oral History Program initiated by Trust President James Cuno and conducted by Martin Meeker, oral historian with The Oral History Center, Bancroft Library, University of California Berkeley. Interviews and video clips may be viewed under the Getty Trust project on the Berkeley Oral History Center website.
  - Irwin, Robert with Jim Duggan: Robert Irwin's Central Garden at the Getty Museum, 2016 (Box 2017.IA.61-01)
  - Lamelas, David: David Lamelas: A Pioneer in Conceptual Art, 2017 (Box 2021.IA.17-03)
  - Ortiz-Torres, Rubén, 2017; Video and sound recordings. No transcript. (Box 2023.IA.14-01)
  - Ruscha, Edward: Ed Ruscha: Artist, 2015 (Box 2016.IA.34-01)
  - Stoner, Joyce Hill: Joyce Hill Stoner: My Life in Art Conservation and Intersections with the Getty, 2019 (Box 2021.IA.17-01)
  - Terrill, Joey: Joey Terrill: At the Forefront of Queer Chicano Art, 2017 (Box 2018.IA.76-01)
- Interviews of significant Getty trustees and staff, 2016-2022; 1.5 Linear Feet; 154 GB
  Records currently consist of the printed transcript and Word, PDF, MP3 and MP4, wav, and raw video files, dating 2016-2022, of the oral histories created as a part of the new 2015- Getty Oral History Program initiated by Trust President James Cuno and overseen by Martin Meeker, oral historian with The Oral History Center, Bancroft Library, University of California Berkeley. Interviews and video clips may be viewed under the Getty Trust project on the Berkeley Oral History Center website.
  This portion of the 2015-ongoing Getty Oral History Project continues conducting interviews with significant Getty trustees and staff, commencing with the departure of former President and CEO Barry Munitz in 2006, and using a thematic approach, e.g., "the resolution of the governance crisis in 2006-2007 (Attorney General investigation, LA Times articles, etc.)," "the negotiations with Italy and Greece over the return of antiquities," "the hiring of Jim Wood as President/CEO," "the response to the financial crisis," "Jim Wood's tenure as President/CEO," "the development of the individual Programs since 2006," and "reflections of the Trustees upon their departure," among other topics.
  - Agnew, Neville, Getty Conservation Institute: Neville Agnew: Thirty Years of Cultural Heritage Site Conservation with the Getty Trust, July 2016; (2 copies) (Box 2016.IA.34-01)
  - Considine, Brian, J. Paul Getty Museum: Conservation and Craftsmanship: Brian Considine, Senior Conservator of Decorative Arts & Architecture at the J. Paul Getty Museum, 2017; (2 copies) (Box 2017.IA.61-01)
  - Dardes, Kathleen: Kathleen Dardes: My Years in Conservation, 1981-2019 (Box 2021.IA.17-03)
  - Druzik, Jim, Getty Conservation Institute: Foxes and Hedgehogs: Jim Druzik and the Development of the Field of Conservation Science, July 2016; (2 copies) (Box 2016.IA.34-01)
  - Gaehtgens, Thomas, Getty Research Institute: Thomas Gaehtgens: Fifty Years of Scholarship and Innovation in Art History, from the Free University of Berlin to the Getty Research Institute, 2022 (Box 2023.IA.14-01)
  - Hamma, Kenneth, J. Paul Getty Museum and J. Paul Getty Trust: Kenneth Hamma: Antiquities and Technology at the Getty (Box 2021.IA.17-01)
    Transcript only.
  - Hartwig, Ron A, Vice President of Communications, J. Paul Getty Trust: Ron A. Hartwig: A Career in Communications [SEALED until August 1, 2023], 2018
    Conditions Governing Access
    This transcript has been sealed in its entirety by Ron Hartwig until August 1, 2023.
  - Hibbard, Sally: Sally Hibbard: Forty Years of Change at the J. Paul Getty Museum, 2019 (Box 2021.IA.17-03)
  - Kozberg, Joanne Corday, Trustee: Joanne Corday Kozberg: The Getty Trust from a Trustee's Perspective, 2005-2017, 2018 (Box 2018.IA.76-01)
  - Kren, Thomas, J. Paul Getty Museum: Thomas Kren: My Thirty-Nine Years as a Curator at the Getty SEALED UNTIL 2026, 2019
  - Leonard, Mark: Mark Leonard: Building New Traditions in Paintings Conservation at the Getty, 1983-2010, 2020 (Box 2021.IA.17-03)
  - Podany, Jerry, J. Paul Getty Museum: Jerry Podany: Four Decades of Conserving Antiquities at the Getty Museum, 2022 (Box 2023.IA.14-01)
    This interview transcript has been substantially edited by the narrator. Audiovisual will only be available upon request, and researchers may not use it for quotes or clips where it differs too widely from the edited transcript.
  - Price, Merritt, J. Paul Getty Museum: Merritt Price: Building the Design Department at the Getty, 2020 (Box 2021.IA.17-01)
  - Schilling, Michael R, Getty Conservation Institute: Michael R. Schilling: Chemical Analysis of Art at the Getty Conservation Institute, 2019 (Box 2021.IA.17-01)
  - Siart, Bill, Trustee: A Life of Service in Art and Education: Bill Siart and the Getty Board of Trustees, 2018 (Box 2018.IA.76-01)
  - Szafran, Yvonne, J. Paul Getty Museum: Yvonne Szafran: Forty Years of Painting Conservation at the J. Paul Getty Museum, 2018 (Box 2021.IA.17-01)
  - Taylor, Peter J., Trustee: Peter J. Taylor: The Getty Trust from a Trustee's Perspective, 2005-2017, 2019 (Box 2019.IA.101-01)
  - Woodworth, Patricia, Vice President, Chief Operations Office, and Chief Financial Officer, J. Paul Getty Trust: Patricia Woodworth: Patricia Woodworth on Getty Trust Finances and Operations [SEALED until January 1, 2029], 2018
    This interview is sealed until January 1, 2029.